So today's דף daf. *Daf* is ס"ז *Samech Zayin* but we're behind,
so we pick up with the last line of ס"ו עמוד א'
*Samech Vav Amud Aleph*, the משנה Mishna *Mishnah*. And we're dealing with
a husband appointing a שליח shaliach *Shaliach*, different language he uses, when
what he says כתבו kisvu *Kitvu* we assume that it means תנו
snu. *Tnu*,
what if you don't exactly see him, and so on. Now the
next משנה Mishna *Mishnah* is going to turn to this issue about
whether it has to be the people he appointed directly or whether
they can then hand over that responsibility to someone else. אמר amar
לשנים *Amar lishnayim*: תנו tenu גט get, לאשתי *Tnu get l'ishti*—he says
to two people, give a גט get *get* to my wife, so
תנו tenu *Tnu*, you can't give it unless you write it, obviously
that includes writing it. או לשלשה *O lishloshah* or he says to
three people, כתבו kisvu גט get, ותנו usnu לאשתי *Kitvu get u-tnu
l'ishti*, write a גט get, *get* and give it to my wife,
הרי אלו יכתבו ויתנו harei elu yichtevu v'yitnu. *harei elu yichtevu v'yitnu*,
then it has to be they themselves who are doing it. Now,
אמר amar לשלשה *amar lishloshah*, but here's the exception and here we
see why the משנה Mishna, *Mishnah* divided the case of כתבו kisvu
*Kitvu* from תנו *Tnu*—from תנו *Tnu*, excuse me, from כתבו ותנו kisvu
usnu. *Kitvu u-tnu*, because אמר amar לשלשה *amar lishloshah*: תנו גט get
לאשתי *Tnu get l'ishti*, if he says to three, give a גט
get. *get* to my wife, so without the כתבו kisvu *Kitvu*, the
thinking is, or the assumption is that without the כתבו ktovu, *Kitvu*,
תנו *Tnu* means to some degree take the responsibility to see that
it is given or it could mean that, right? Because you're not
specifically indicating every action that needs to be done. So therefore, the
assumption in the משנה mishna, *Mishnah* is, well, when it's two, nevertheless,
we're not going to interpret it that way because two are the
people, you know, they're not a body that normally delegates responsibility. They
would be the people to do it themselves. But three is a
בית דין beis din *Beis Din*. And a בית דין beis din
*Beis Din* could be understood as a body that supervises things and
not necessarily does things personally. So when you say כתבו ktovu, תנו
*Kitvu Tnu* to the three people, then you're talking, then you're being
very concrete about the actions and you mean that they themselves have
to do it.
Well, presumably what it means is is that, well yes, I mean
we're going to see in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* or the end
of the משנה mishna *Mishnah*, if you don't say כולכם kulchem, *Kulchem*,
you say to a group of people and you don't say כולכם
kulchem, *Kulchem*, it means from among you, so two people would sign
it, one person would give it, גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s going to discuss
who actually has to do the scribing, but nevertheless it has to
be done by some distribution of the three of them. However, if
you say the three תנו *Tnu* and you're not specifically identifying the
concrete actions that need to be done, then that's interpreted as to
supervise, make sure that it's done, being given over the responsibility to
a בית דין beis din *Beis Din*, and then they can appoint
someone. So אמר amar לשלשה *amar lishloshah*: תנו גט get, לאשתי *Tnu
get l'ishti*, הרי אלו יאמרו לאחרים ויכתבו *harei elu yomru l'acherim v'yichtevu*,
they are able to say to other people, they don't have to,
and they can and other people can write it, מפני שעשאן בית
דין beis din דברי רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir, *mipnei she'asan Beis Din,
divrei Rabbi Meir*, he made them into a בית דין Beis Din
*Beis Din* and gave them that role because that's according to רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir*. וזו הלכה halacha? העלה רבי Rebbi חנינא
איש אונו Chanina Ish Ono מבית האסורים *V'zo halacha he'ela Rabbi Chanina
ish Ono mibeis ha-asurim*, and this is the הלכה halacha *halacha* that
רבי Rebbi. חנינא איש אונו *Rabbi Chanina ish Ono* brought from the
prison, and רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says it means from the, in the
name of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva, *Rabbi Akiva* who was being held
in prison because of, you know, because of the edicts, the Roman
edicts. מקובלני באומר לשלשה *Mekubalani b'omer lishloshah*: תנו גט get? לאשתי *Tnu
get l'ishti*, I have a tradition, presumably saying this in the name
of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva *Rabbi Akiva*, that if somebody says that
you say to three people, give a גט get *get* to my
wife לאשתי *l'ishti*, שיאמרו לאחרים ויכתבו *she'yomru l'acherim v'yichtevu*, that they can
give that over to other people, מפני שעשאן בית דין *mipnei she'asan
Beis Din*, because he made them into a בית דין *Beis Din*.
אמר amar רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi *Amar Rabbi Yosi*, רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yosi *Rabbi Yosi* says: נומנו לשליח *nomnu lishaliach*, we said to the
שליח shaliach? *shaliach*. נומנו *Nomnu* is a interesting, it just means אמרנו
*amarnu*, but it's like an archaic version of that word. We said
to the שליח shaliach *shaliach*: אף אנו מקובלין *af anu mekubalin*, yeah,
that's your tradition? Let me tell you what my tradition is. My
tradition is שאפילו אמר amar לבית דין הגדול שבירושלים *she-afillu amar l'Beis
Din HaGadol she-bi-Yerushalayim*, even were he to say to the High Court
in Jerusalem: תנו גט get לאשתי *Tnu get l'ishti*, give a גט
get *get* to my wife, you didn't say כתבו ksovu *Kitvu* and
obviously they're a בית דין *Beis Din*, it's not just any three
people, they're clearly a בית דין *Beis Din*, and you know, you
wouldn't assume the like you said to the Supreme Court, you wouldn't
assume the justices would then start taking out parchment and start like
writing themselves. Nevertheless, that's what you said. So if they want to
if they want to do it and they want to get a
גט get? *get* to your wife, do you know what they have
to do? שילמדו ויכתבו ויתנו *she-yilmedu v'yichtevu v'yitnu*, they have to learn
how to write a גט get *get* and write it themselves and
well, they don't have to, you can always appoint other people, but
if if the גט get? *get* is going to be given through
this appointment, it can only be given through they themselves doing it
directly. They can always reject it, say, you know what, because you
told me to do it I have to do it?
Meaning they can't say, alright we'll supervise it.
Correct, that's his point. His point is he rejects the earlier פסק
psak *psak* of the משנה mishna. *Mishnah*, and even if it's clearly
a בית דין *Beis Din* and clearly that was your intent, it
seems, or it's we don't really care about the intent maybe, the
words you said were you should write and therefore, or you should
give, and that means you have to do it personally. הרי אלו
יכתבו ויתנו *harei elu yichtevu v'yitnu*. Now, אמר amar לעשרה *amar l'asara*,
now switching gears, which relates to the earlier part of the משנה
mishna *Mishnah* but it's a different point, if you say to ten
people: כתבו ksovu תנו גט get, לאשתי *Kitvu tnu get l'ishti*, write
a גט get *get* and give it to my wife. And since
you say כתבו kisvu. *Kitvu* clearly you did not mean that they
supervise, you meant they should do it themselves. So the question is
what do you do when you say it to more than just
one person? How is that interpreted? אחד כותב ושנים חותמים *echad kotev
u-shnayim chotmim*, it means among you, you have to write and give
a גט get *get* to my wife. כולכם kulchem, כתבו, kisvu he
says over explicitly all of you write
a גט, get. then אחד כותב וכולם חותמים, echad koteiv ve'chulam chotmim,
one writes and they all sign. And because that's now the question
is, but they're not all writing. Is there has to be... does,
now this is going to be the first question the גמרא Gemara
asks, which we've sort of been eliding, which is how much does
the word כתבו kisvu here mean sign, and how much does it
mean actually scribe the גט get itself? Okay, but it certainly seems
from the משנה mishna. that כתבו's fundamental meaning is signing because if
as all of them have to sign and only one of them
has to write, but not necessarily, because all of them can sign.
Like signatures, you can just add signatures. Whereas I suppose it's like
when they write a ספר תורה, Sefer Torah, you're going to fill
in a little letter because you bought... I suppose multiple people could
write, but it's just not practical and you don't... it's not really
the same type of a phenomenon. So in that case, even if
the כתבו כולכם kisvu kulchem is about the writing of the גט,
get not the signing, or also means the writing of the גט,
get nevertheless, we're going to interpret it that one person writes on
behalf of all of them. What we're going to say, not to
ruin the surprise, but what we're going to say in the גמרא
Gemara. is if they all have to be physically present. When he
doesn't say כולכם, kulcham, he just means among you. So seven people
can leave and two people can take care of it. But when
he says all of you, so all to sign is obvious, everybody
signs. All to write means everybody is present, it's sort of like
a
שליח ציבור. shaliach tzibur. Everybody is present and one person represents the
group and is writing it for the group. One minute. לפיכך אם
מת אחד מהם הרי זה גט בטל. Lefichach im meis echad meihen
harei zeh get batel. If one of them dies, the גט get
is no good because I demanded, I required, thank you, that everybody
be part of the writing of the גט. get Again, what you
see here, by the way, that's interesting is, and we've seen this
before, but it's worth pointing out, is how much the husband controls
about this process. Meaning he can actually determine, it's that that this
is a פסול גט pasul get because it was not done according
to exactly his wishes. You might have said, whatever, there's only one
type of גט, get it has a particular text, it's signed by
two witnesses,
so you could sort of say, I refuse to make somebody a
שליח shaliach to give it, but how do you מבטל mevatel the
גט? get, And again we see that the דעת da'at and the
רצון ratzon of the husband is really central
to the shaping, what is the nature of the גט get, itself.
And if he wants a גט get, in a particular way and
it's not done in that way, then the גט get. itself is
בטל. batel. Yes, you have a question?
Wait, are we saying that if more than one person wrote the
actual document, it would be a valid גט?
get
Yeah, that could be, sure. But the משנה mishna doesn't imagine that
that's a practical thing. So we're going to interpret "all of you
write," if it's talking about the scribing, the way the גמרא's gemara
going to clarify, is that everybody's present and one person writes. But
"all of you sign," or to the degree that the word write
includes signing, which it does seem so in this משנה, mishna then
that's easy. Everybody just affixes their signature. Okay, so let's take a
look at the גמרא. gemara אמר רבי ירמיה בר אבא שלחו מבי
רב לשמואל. Amar Rabi Yirmeya bar Abba shalchu mibei Rav l'Shmuel. They
sent from the ישיבה yeshiva of רב Rav to שמואל, Shmuel, which
is just a fascinating phenomenon in itself too, because I mean why
didn't they ask this question to רב? Rav? Okay, I don't know,
maybe he was on vacation, maybe he was out sick. Anyway, or
maybe, I don't know, maybe it was after... I don't actually know
who died first, whether רב Rav died before... anyway it's fascinating because
רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel were contemporaries, generally assumed to be of
equal stature. And here they're sending from the ישיבה yeshiva of רב
Rav to שמואל Shmuel the following question. ילמדנו רבנו, Yelamdeinu rabbeinu, let
our master teach us. אמר לשניים כתבו ותנו גט לאשתי. Amar l'shnayim
kisvu utnu get l'ishti. If you say to two people, and remember,
two is not a בית דין regardless, it has to be they
themselves. So you say to two people, כתבו ותנו גט לאשתי, kisvu
utnu get l'ishti, אמרו לסופר וכתב וחתמו הן מהו? amru l'sofer ve'chasav
ve'chasmu hein mahu? But they didn't write it. They had a סופר
sofer write it and they signed it. What's the הלכה? halakha, Because
basically what they are asking is does the... when you say כתבו
and they have to do it themselves, does כתבו mean the writing
of the גט get, or does it mean the signing of the
גט? get Okay, and especially since the emphasis here, שניים חותמים, shnayim
chotmim, אמר לשניים, amar l'shnayim, כתבו גט לאשתי, kisvu get l'ishti, clearly
the reason you need two is because you need two witnesses. All
right, but that's the question. Does it also mean that the writing
has to be done by they themselves? Okay, so שלח להו, shalach
lehu, he sends back to them, תצא והדבר צריך תלמוד. teitzei vehadavar
tzarich talmud. No, you know what?
She has to... and תצא teitzei means like if presumably if she
got remarried on the basis of this גט, get she can't stay
with her second husband because it's a questionable גט get in that
case. But I need to look into it more. I'm not sure
that it's not good, but it's a ספק גט safek get in
that case, whether they only... if they didn't do the actual scribing
themselves. So מאי והדבר צריך תלמוד? mai vehadavar tzarich talmud? What do
you have to investigate? So אילימא משום דהוי ליה מילי ומיספקא לן
מילי אם מימסרן לשליח אי לא מימסרן לשליח? eileima mishum d'havei lei
mili umisafka lan mili im mimsaran l'shaliach i lo mimsaran l'shaliach? This
is going to be our basic theme for the remainder of the
דף. daf. Are words given over to a שליח? shaliach, What that
means is a שליחות shlichus that does not come with a physical
concrete thing. For example, remember when the husband makes a שליח shaliach
to deliver גט get to his wife, he's giving the שליח shaliach
a physical גט. get So for that שליח, shaliach if that שליח
shaliach gets sick, you might remember cases where the שליח shaliach got
sick and he appointed
and that could be handed over. Okay, but if the woman appoints
a שליח shaliach, to receive a גט get, for her and that
שליח shaliach gets sick, it's not so obvious that he can, or
not only not so obvious, it seems very questionable whether he can
appoint a שליח shaliach, to take his place because he only has
a verbal sort of, you know, appointment and there's nothing, and therefore
he might not be in a position to pass that over. For
you to represent the woman, you know, you need to hear it
directly from the woman. For me, who am only her agent, for
me I don't have that authority to pass over and to make
you an agent in her stead. If I had that physical גט
get that represents my role or whatever, then the act of giving
over the גט get sort of starts to create that sense of
agency. But words alone cannot necessarily be passed on, you know, a
verbal appointment cannot necessarily be passed on. So that's the question by
a woman's שליח לקבלה shaliach lekabala making another שליח לקבלה, shaliach lekabala,
and it's also the issue about appointing שליחין shlichin to write a
גט get, before the גט get exists. Okay, so the question is
if I tell these two people write a גט get for my
wife
and they can't have somebody else do it in their stead because
that's מילי, mili, it's verbal and
it's not given over for them to pass on. Now that by
the way is pretty much the presumption of the entire משנה, mishna,
right? The entire משנה mishna is if I said you guys write
it, then I mean like only you and you can't pass it
on to somebody else, okay, and so let's take a look at
how the גמרא gemara sort of frames this issue.
Is there some presumption, like let's say these guys don't know how
to write and you know that?
Right, so that's going to be where the גמרא gemara is going
to go. So let's take a look.
So if the question whether they can have somebody else write it,
scribe it, I'll use that word to make it clear, if the
question whether they can have somebody else scribe it is whether they
can pass on their agency to somebody else, their verbal agency. Now
of course that would be funny because if that was the question,
they should also be able to pass on the agency to sign
the גט, get right? It wouldn't be a distinction between writing and
signing. But anyway, if that's your question, משום דהוי מילי ומספקא ליה
מילי מימסרן לשליח ולא, mishum dehavai mili u-misafklei mili mimtzarnu lishlicha v'lo,
yes he meant for them to scribe it, but the question that's
being asked is can they pass that on to somebody else? והאמר
שמואל אמר רב הלכה כרבי יוסי, veha-amar Shmuel amar Rav halacha ke-Rabbi
Yosi, we rule like רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi in our משנה. mishna
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi in our משנה mishna says even the בית
דין הגדול שבירושלים, Beis Din Hagadol sheb'Yerushalayim, right, has to do it
themselves. So רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi clearly holds as a fundamental thing
there is no way an agency can be passed on. You know,
it sounds that that might have been the assumption of the תנא
קמא Tanna Kamma as well, but clearly that's רבי יוסי's Rabbi Yosei
position. And so he says, so שמואל Shmuel himself says we rule
like רבי יוסי Rebbe Yosi דאמר מילי לא מימסרן לשליח. de-amar mili
lo mimtzarnu lishlicha. A verbal agency cannot be passed on even if
it's to the בית דין הגדול. Beis Din Hagadol. And if that's
how שמואל Shmuel rules, so how could they have had somebody else
scribe it?
אלא לשמואל הכי קמיבעיא ליה. ela le-Shmuel hachi kamiba'ei lei. No, שמואל
Shmuel knows that you can't pass on a verbal agency, but here's
the question about having somebody else scribe it. האי כתבו, hai ktovu,
when the husband says write it, כתב ידם כתב הגט, ktav yadam
ktav ha-get, does he mean scribe it or does he mean, sorry,
does he mean sign it or does he mean scribe it? Okay.
So the גמרא gemara is going to, so if he means scribe
it, then they can't have somebody else scribe it for them, מילי
לא מימסרן לשליח. mili lo mimtzarnu lishlicha. If he means sign it,
then we're going to see in a minute they're not taking their
appointment and passing it on. Then as Michael said, if I just
told you guys sign it and I didn't say scribe it, then
implicitly what I am saying is find somebody to write the גט,
get. so you're not passing on your agency, you're essentially just communicating
to a third party my appointment of that third party. You got
that? Okay. So that's going to be the point. All right. כתב
ידם כתב הגט תפשוט ליה ממתניתין. ktav yadam ktav ha-get tifshot lei
mimatnisin. Learn it from our משנה. Mishnah. אמר לשנים תנו גט לאשתי
amar lishnayim tnu get l'ishti or לשלושה כתבו ותנו גט לאשתי. lishlosha
kitvu u-tnu get l'ishti. הרי אלו יכתבו ויתנו. So it says that
they have to write it. So it sounds like you're appointing them
to scribe it themselves. No. הגופא קמיבעיא ליה. haguva kamiba'ei lei. No,
that itself is our question. כתבו, when it says in the משנה
Mishnah. that they have to write it, כתב ידם הוא או כתב
הגט הוא, ktav yadam hu o ktav ha-get hu, does it mean
that they have to sign it or does it mean that they
have to scribe it? That's what we want to know. Our משנה
Mishnah talks about writing and delivering. To what degree does that mean
signing, or to what degree does that also mean scribing? Now, so,
well
also the really point is that the proof should have been from
the end of the משנה, Mishnah because the end of the משנה
Mishna, says if you say it to ten people, it says one
of them writes it and two of them sign it. So it
sounds like, no, besides that you could have said כתבו, but it
sounds like that somebody in that group has to be the scriber,
right? You cannot have... has to be the scribe, right? So it's
not exactly clear. But anyway, that's the גמרא's gemara question. Okay, so
now the גמרא gemara still wants to understand, okay fine, but let's
say you didn't mean scribe it, how could you get somebody else
to do it? Right? So the גמרא Gemara says,
פשיטא דכתב הגט הוא. pishita dektav ha-get hu. The גמרא Gemara says
one minute, it obviously means scribe it. דתני סיפא אמר רבי יוסי
נמנו ושבחו אף אנו מקובלים שאפילו אמר לבית דין הגדול שבירושלים תנו
גט לאשתי שיהיו לומדים ויכתבו ויתנו, de-tani seifa amar Rabbi Yosei neminu
ve-shavu ach af anu mekubbalim she-afillu amar le-veis din ha-gadol she-bi-yerushalayim tenu
get le-ishti she-yihyu lomedim ve-yikhtevu ve-yitenu, even if it's the בית דין
הגדול, Beis Din Ha-Gadol, they would have to learn how to do
it. So אי אמרת i amart בשלמא bishleima כתב הגט, ksav ha-get,
if you said it means the scribing of the גט, get, so
שפיר, shapira, we could understand that you could be a בית דין
on the בית דין and not know how to scribe a גט.
get Okay, that's a different specialty.
I don't know if they'd know how to do it.
They know 70 languages but okay. But anyway maybe. Anyway, but at
least we could make sense of it. שפיר. shapira. אלא אי אמרת
כתב ידם הוא, ella i amart ksav yadam hu, if it meant
was to sign it, so מי איכא בית דינא דלא ידעי מיכתם
חתימת ידים? mi ka beis dina d'lo yadi michtam chasimas yadayim? How
can you say oh they'll have to learn how to sign their
signatures and sign it? Right, it's obviously absurd that that's not what
the משנה Mishna, means. So it's a pretty darn good proof that
the משנה Mishna means the actual scribing. So the גמרא Gemara though
is דחי docha this. אין, in, yes, איכא בית דינא חדתא, ika
beis dina chatata, there could be a brand new בית דין that
has yet to learn how to sign their names. I don't know.
There's a בית דין הגדול שבירושלים Beis Din Ha-Gadol she-bi-Yerushalayim
just sworn in, a totally new בית דין הגדול שבירושלים. Beis Din
Ha-Gadol she-bi-Yerushalayim. Actually, now there's the whole thing about Scalia dying. I
was looking up some things about like what are the criteria about
being a Supreme Court justice and I was reminded that in the
Constitution there are no criteria. No, you don't have to even like
know the law. Like anybody could be a supreme, whoever the president,
I mean he has to go through, be approved by the Senate
or whatever. Okay, anyway, so okay, it's a bad answer. But we're
still asking our question. Maybe it just means sign and it doesn't
mean scribe. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this, ואי
סבירא לן דהאי כתבו כתב ידם הוא. ve-i svira lan d'hai ksovu
ksav yadam hu. One minute, but if כתבו means sign it and
it does not mean scribe and therefore they can have somebody else
scribe it, כתב הגט כשר, ksav ha-get kasher, but so that they
can have somebody else do the scribing. והא אמר שמואל אמר רב
אמר רבי הלכה כרבי יוסי דאמר מילי לא מימסרו לשליח. ve-ha amar
Shmuel amar Rav amar Rebbe halacha k'Rabbi Yosei d'amar milu lo nimseru
l'shaliach. How have you gotten, and I've already answered this question for
you, but the גמרא's Gemara now finally coming back and saying how
did you get around your מילי mili problem? They're still finding another
person and having that other person scribe it. So the גמרא Gemara
says, אמרי, amri, look, אי סבירא לן דכתבו כתב ידם הוא, i
svira lan d'ksovu ksav yadam hu, if when he says write it
it means sign it and they were telling these two to sign
and not to
scribe, כתב הגט נעשה כאומר אמרו. ksav ha-get na'aseh k'omer imru. It's
like saying say to them to say to others. ומודה רבי יוסי
באומר אמרו, u-modei Rabbi Yosei b'omer imru, and רבי יוסי Rebbe Yosi
would agree by אומר omer means the בעל ba'al says to the
two people, אמרו, imru, say to somebody else that this is what
they should do. All right, which means that there's two issues. One
is the question of maybe for somebody to be my שליח, shaliach.
and this could be a question in שליחות shlichus in כל התורה
כולה, kol ha-Torah kullah, but it's particularly an issue about גט get,
with this strong emphasis of לשמה lishmah and the בעל ba'al and
the בעל'ס ba'al's דעת da'as controlling it, which I mentioned before. So
let's at least raise this question by גט, get although what the
הלכה in general שליחות shlichus is is a separate level of a
question. But at least by a גט get you could say for
somebody to be my שליח shaliach in the writing or the signing
or the giving, then they have to hear it directly from me.
Okay, and therefore that sort of sense of creating that direct connection
with me is necessary. Maybe you could make a distinction. Maybe that's
necessary for the writing because the פסוק pasuk says וכתב לה ספר
כריתות, ve-khasav lah sefer krisus, so maybe for him to write, for
it to be like my writing, maybe has to hear directly from
me. Maybe other things, signing, maybe less so. Okay, who knows? But
that's one idea which is for him to really represent me and
to be a real appointment he has to hear it directly from
me. That would be a position that אומר אמרו omer imru is
no good. I can't even say to Michael, Michael, you know, go
tell Jenna to write the גט get for me, okay? Because even
though effectively I am really appointing Jenna not in her presence, right?
I mean I've then and Michael is just sort of just informing
her, but that wouldn't be good because for her to be my
scribe she has to hear it directly from me. That's a position
that אומר אמרו omer imru is no good. But you could easily
understand no, no, no, that's okay. I appointed Jenna, Michael's just telling
her, okay? But the other, but the next level is I'm saying
to Michael, Michael, you write the גט get for me and Michael's
saying you know I really don't have time I'm going to ask
Jenna to do it for me. Then that's a much bigger question.
I didn't appoint Jenna. Does he have the authority to appoint her
to represent to take over his שליחות? shlichus? That's whether מילי לא
מימסרו לשליח. mili lo nimseru l'shaliach. So what the גמרא Gemara says
is a very reasonable sort of split פסק paskens on this, which
is שמואל Shmuel could hold מילי לא מימסרו לשליח. mili lo nimseru
l'shaliach. If I appointed you you've got to do it yourself. You
do not have the authority to pass it on. Again, if it's
a physical גט get, that might the גט get might represent your
authority and maybe that could be passed on, but in this case
it's just words, you don't have that authority. But אומר אמרו omer
imru is okay. If I'm telling you to inform someone they don't
have to hear it directly from me. So if כתבו means sign
it, I tell two people sign the גט, okay, what I'm implicitly
saying is find someone to write it. That person you're going to
find to write it will be my שליח, you'll inform that person,
but you're being told now אומר אמרו, omer imru, you're being told
to find that person, that would be good. Okay, so that is
the question. When you say to two write a גט does it
mean sign it and they can find someone to write it? Or
does it mean, you know, write it and they have to write
it themselves? Yes.
What about the writing.
What?
You're not talking about the delivery?
The delivering they would have to do because I said כתבו ותנו.
kisvu usnu.
So they would have to do it?
Yeah, I said כתבו ותנו. The only thing is that the only
thing is... the question is what's the scope of the word כתבו.
Okay, right. That's the question. But let's take a look now as
גמרא Gemara. continues.
Doesn't ותנו mean make sure it gets delivered to her? Even if
they point to other people to deliver it?
Well we might say it in a case of three people and
so on when you just said תנו. Okay, but right, but normally
we wouldn't. Correct.
So why are we not saying the same thing?
Because the word כתבו could have a scope to mean חתמו. chasmu.
And then I haven't appointed you to write it.
But כתבו means חתמו? chasmu?
I understand. All right, so that's the question. But on the other
hand we have you saying to two people, right, it was really
about writing and I you know, anyways, that's the question. Okay, so
גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay. ומי מודה רבי יוסי באומר אמרו?
Umi modei Rebbe Yosi b'omer imru? Does רבי יוסי Rebbe Yosi really
agree that אומר אמרו omer imru is okay? והתנן, Veha tanan, we
learn in the משנה. Mishna כתב סופר ועד. Ksav sofer ve'eid. If
you have something that only has an עד אחד eid echad but
it has the handwriting of the סופר. sofer. So does the fact...
the סופר sofer
always has the handwriting of the סופר. sofer. I know. So the
סופר sofer isn't the עד. eid. You have a different person who's
the עד, eid, okay, maybe it means... and the question is, can
you say the סופר sofer implicitly is an עד? eid? Because his
actual writing of the גט is implicitly testifying to what's being written
down. Is that good? כשר, Kasher, that's כשר. kasher. That's one version
of the משנה. Mishna ואמר רבי ירמיה בר אבא, Va'amar Rebbe Yirmiyah
bar Abba, רבי ירמיה Rebbe Yirmiyah says, חתם סופר שנינו. chasam sofer
shaninu.
By the way, this is the, you know, you know the חתם
סופר Chasam Sofer and you know what his son called his ספר,
sefer, the כתב סופר. Ksav Sofer. So it's basically from this גמרא.
Gemara. So yeah, sure, of course. חתם סופר Chasam Sofer and כתב
סופר. Ksav Sofer. So anyway, חתם סופר שנינו. chasam sofer shaninu. No,
no, no. It's not... no, the... if the handwriting of the סופר
sofer would not be good. The question is, the סופר sofer was
one of the עדים eidim plus another עד. eid. That's what the
משנה Mishna is saying. That's כשר. kasher. Okay, that doesn't seem like
a חידוש chiddush at all. Okay. ואמר חסדא מתניתין מני רבי יוסי
היא דאמר מילו לא נמסרו לשליח. Ve'amar Chisda matnitin mani Rebbe Yosi
hi d'amar milu lo nimseru l'shaliach. And our משנה Mishna over there
is going like רבי יוסי Rebbe Yosi. that says words are not
given over to a שליח. Now
we're going to see why. We're going to see how that's at
all relevant. Okay, so גמרא's Gemara going to spell it out. Okay,
so let's keep on reading the גמרא. Gemara ואי סלקא דעתך מודה
רבי יוסי באומר אמרו. Ve'i salka daitach modei Rebbe Yosi b'omer imru.
Now if רבי יוסי Rebbe Yosi would agree that אומר אמרו omer
imru would be okay to inform somebody as you know that I've
appointed them. So נפקא מינה חורבא, nafka minah churbah, destruction will come
out of it. It'll be terrible. What will be terrible? So דזימנין
דאמר להו לשנים. dezimnin d'amar lehu lishnayim. I'll say to two people.
אמרו לסופר ויכתוב ולפלוני ופלוני ויחתמו. Imru l'sofer veyichtov uleploni u'ploni veyechtemu.
I'll say to them, go tell the סופר sofer that's אומר אמרו,
omer imru, right. Go tell the סופר sofer to write it and
tell ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon to sign it.
ומשום כיסופא דסופר. Umishum kisufa desofer. But now these... this... these people
that I made these messengers to inform the proper people, because I'm
allowed to make them messengers to inform people, right, because אומר אמרו
omer imru is okay. Everybody with me? So if אומר אמרו omer
imru is okay, I've appointed somebody Michael to go find a סופר,
sofer, find, get so-and-so as a סופר sofer and get ראובן Reuven
and שמעון Shimon as the witnesses. Now Michael says, the סופר sofer
is going to be offended. He's going to say what, you had
to get two other witnesses? I'm good enough to write the גט,
I'm not good enough to sign it? You don't think I'm a
כשר עד? kosher eid? So because Michael is so understand... is so
concerned about the... about the embarrassment of the סופר, sofer, משום כיסופא
דסופר חיישי, mishum kisufa desofer chaishi,
he's afraid, ומחתמי חד מהני וסופר בהדייהו. u'machtimei chad mehani v'sofer bahadaihu.
And he'll just change my שליחות shlichus a little bit and he'll
say סופר sofer you be an עד eid and I'll get ראובן
Reuven and I'm not going to get שמעון. Shimon. Okay. ובעל לא
אמר
הכי. Ubaal lo amar hachi. And I didn't say that. So the
גט is פסול pasul but people will think the גט is כשר.
kasher. So basically what the גמרא's Gemara saying is that חתם סופר
ועד chasam sofer ve'eid to us we can easily imagine a scenario
where the סופר sofer wasn't intended to be an עד eid but
he was made an עד eid because you were... you were afraid
to tell him that you know to get other people. The גמרא
Gemara imagines that that's a common... a likely scenario. And therefore the
גמרא Gemara says there's no way we would allow this גט to
be good because we'd have to be concerned about that scenario. You
know the only way we wouldn't have to be concerned about that
scenario is if the husband had to appoint people directly. Is if
אומר אמרו omer imru was no good and the husband had to
appoint people directly there would be no concern that the message would
have been misrepresented. All right. So that's why we said חתם סופר
ועד chasam sofer ve'eid is רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yossi It presumed that
according to רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi. everybody heard here everything straight from
the husband. And then חתם סופר chasam sofer is not going to
be a problem. But if it's a way that I can tell
somebody to tell other people, so how do we allow חתם סופר?
chasam sofer? Right, that could easily be that they got embarrassed and
it wasn't what I intended. So the גמרא Gemara says, אם לא,
כיון דאמר מר כשר ולא תעשה כן בישראל. am lo, kivan d'amar
mar kasher velo ta'aseh ken beYisrael. Since we say yes, it is
כשר, kasher, חתם סופר, chasam sofer, but it should never do something
like this. Okay, we'll see why, not because of this concern. There's
another concern that will come out of the bottom of the... that
גמרא's Gemara going to raise at the bottom of the דף. But
for whatever reason we say that yes, בדיעבד bedieved it's כשר kasher
but you should never do this thing, which means that if the
סופר sofer is told you're going to sign it plus one other
עד eid then the סופר sofer should refuse. Not only should the
husband not appoint anybody, but the סופר sofer should refuse to do
that type of a thing. So once that's true, לא שכיח *lo
shechiach*, we're not afraid that this bad scenario will come out about
it. Okay, so we tried to say that this scenario works חתם
סופר Chasam Sofer *Chasam Sofer* because they have to hear it directly
from the husband, which proves that רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi. *Rabbi Yosi*
says אומר אמרו omer imru, *omer imru* is not good. And the
גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* says no, maybe אומר אמרו omer imru *omer imru*
is good and I understand the scenario you're concerned about, but since
people aren't supposed to do this anyway and the סופר sofer *sofer*
shouldn't listen in such a scenario, so it's not such a big
deal. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says one minute.
The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says ולחוש *v'leichush* I'm not done says the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* because here's another possibility. דילמא אמר להו לבי תרי
אמרו לסופר ויכתוב ואתם חתומו *dilma amar lehu l'vei terei imru l'sofer
veyichtov v'atem chatomu*. Let's say he doesn't say get ראובן *Reuven* and
שמעון *Shimon* to sign. I say to ראובן *Reuven* and שמעון *Shimon*,
I directly appoint them and I say you guys sign just find
somebody else to be the סופר *sofer*. ואזלו אינהו *v'azlu inhu*, so
that presumably the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* assumes is not לא תעשה כן
lo taaseh chen, בישראל *lo ta'aseh kein b'Yisrael*. We'll see later at
the bottom of the דף *daf* that when I have you get,
I don't appoint anybody directly, that's לא תעשה כן בישראל *lo ta'aseh
kein b'Yisrael*. But we're assuming this case where I've appointed the עדים
*edim* directly, okay, but just had them find a סופר *sofer*. We
assume that would be okay. Okay, but that's still going to be
a problem. What's the problem going to come out of it? Okay,
and so these people go ואזלי הנך משום כיסופא דסופר ומחתמי ליה
לסופר בהדי חד מינייהו *v'azli hanach mishum kisufa d'sofer u'machtami lei l'sofer
bahadi chad mineihu*. So they sign, so שמעון *Shimon* decides look the
סופר *sofer* is going to be embarrassed, I won't sign it, let's
just have the סופר *sofer* be one of the signatures. ובעל לא
אמר הכי *u'ba'al lo amar hachi*. And the husband didn't say that.
So again, if רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi *Rabbi Yosi* did not hold
of אומר אמרו omer imru *omer imru* and you had to hear
everything straight from the husband, everybody had to hear everything straight from
the husband, this scenario wouldn't happen. But if the סופר *sofer* can
be appointed not in his presence, there's still a concern of this
scenario and we assume that this is a likely scenario because I'm
appointing at least the עדים *edim* directly. So the גמרא *Gemara* says
no, הא נמי קשיא ולא תעשה הוא *ha nami kashya v'lo ta'aseh
hu*. No, that also you're not allowed to do that לכתחילה *lechatchila*
either. We're not concerned about it. So the גמרא *Gemara* says one
minute, הניחא למאן דאמר קשיא ולא תעשה *haniycha l'man d'amar kashya v'lo
ta'aseh*. We're going to see at the bottom of the דף *daf*
that this is debated. If I directly appoint the witnesses but ask
them to find somebody who to write it,
there's one that says I shouldn't do, I'm not allowed to do
that and the סופר *sofer* shouldn't listen, and there's others that say
I am allowed to do that. So if I am allowed to
do that, מאי איכא למימר *mai ika l'meimar*, what can you say?
So we're back to our question. How do you allow חתם סופר
Chasam Sofer. ועד *Chasam Sofer v'ed*?
Aren't we assuming that that's a scenario where they may be because
of embarrassment got the סופר *sofer* to sign and it wasn't what
the husband wanted? So if רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi *Rabbi Yosi* says
that everything has to be heard directly from the husband, it's not
a concern. But if רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi? *Rabbi Yosi* allows for
אומר אמרו omer imru, *omer imru*, if רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi. *Rabbi
Yosi* allows for the appointment not to be heard directly from the
husband, then we cannot understand how we allow חתם סופר ועד *Chasam
Sofer v'ed*, why we're not concerned about the scenario that we just
described. So the גמרא *Gemara* says okay, אלא *ela* you're right, fine.
Fine. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi. תרתי אמר *Rabbi Yosi tartei amar*. רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yossi *Rabbi Yosi* says both. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi. *Rabbi
Yosi* says you can't have pass on an appointment and you can't
even inform somebody of an appointment that the husband made. מילי לא
מימסרן meili lo mimsaran, *mili lo mimsaran* and אומר אמרו omer imru,
*omer imru* is no good. And therefore חתם סופר *Chasam Sofer* is
okay because according to רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi *Rabbi Yosi* all the
players have to have heard it directly from the husband. Now just
pause here a moment. You know why that actually makes an enormous
amount of sense? Because going back to the משנה Mishna, *mishna*, remember
why are we pinning all of this whole position on מילי meili
*mili* on the משנה Mishna. *mishna*? Because in the משנה Mishna *mishna*
it was רבי Rebbi, יוסי *Rabbi Yosi* who said that you could
tell the בית דין הגדול Beis Din HaGadol בירושלים *Beis Din HaGadol
b'Yerushalayim* and they would have to do it themselves. Now in that
case, I think we could all agree that implicitly that's אומר אמרו
omer imru *omer imru*. Implicitly you did not basically want them to
do it themselves or needed them to do it themselves. You implicitly
meant guys can you supervise it, right? But nevertheless רבי Rebbi יוסי
*Rabbi Yosi* says I don't care, they're the only ones who can
do it, which is a clear point of
the only people who can do the גט *get* are the people
who heard it straight from the husband and even if you gave
it to the בית דין *Beis Din*, I don't care how much
you wanted them to pass that on, they're the only ones who
heard it from you and they're the only ones who can write
it. Okay, so that's רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yosi*'s position. מילי לא מימסרן
לשליח mili lo mimsran leshalich, *mili lo mimsaran l'shliach*. You can't pass
on an appointment, but not only that, אומר אמרו omer imru *omer
imru* is no good. You can't even inform someone that they're to
do it. The only people who can do it is the people
that the husband directly appointed. That's רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yosi*'s position. Yes.
Different underpinning reasons, right? You can't pass on the word because you
don't want that but אומר אמרו omer imru *omer imru* is about
distorting the message.
Yeah, but even if no, no, the distorting message was a concern
by the חתם סופר *Chasam Sofer*. But the problem of אומר אמרו
omer imru *omer imru* is as I was saying before, is a
specific issue that to be, to represent the husband, particularly in משלוח
של גט *mishloach shel get*, it has to come through direct appointment.
Okay, that's why אומר אמרו omer imru *omer imru* is no good.
So
how is that different from מילי meili *mili*?
Because מילי *mili* is that I appointed here well Michael... But I
appointed Michael and Michael might not be empowered to pass on that
that appointment, whereas if I appointed Jen and just asked Michael to
tell her, I have done the appointment of Jen, but it wasn't
direct. I didn't and because I was not directly communicating that to
her, she then that's not a good שליחות. shlichus Okay, so אומר
אמרו, omer imru if that's no good, means somebody can only represent
the husband if they're directly appointed by the husband. מילי means if
you're the one that was given the agency, you don't have the
authority to pass it on. All right, so those are two conceptually
different things. You got it? Are you processing? Fine distinction. It is,
but you certainly understand the issue. One is I've appointed Jen, not
in her presence. Think about it this way: can you make a
שליח שלא בפניו? shaliach shelo befanav? אומר אמרו is saying you cannot
make a שליח שלא בפניו, shaliach shelo befanav, at least by גט.
Okay? מילי is saying you can make a שליח שלא בפניו, shaliach
shelo befanav, but you cannot pass on the שליחות shlichus that you
were given.
Okay? So anyway, so רבי יוסי holds both and that's why the
בית דין הגדול in ירושלים Yerushalayim would have to be the ones
to write it themselves. All right? אלא רבי יוסי תרתי קאמר. ela
Rabbi Yossi tartei ka'amar. ושמואל סבר לה כוותיה בחדא ופליג עליה בחדא.
u'Shmuel savar lah kevasei bechada u'palig alei bechada.
But שמואל, Shmuel, he's the one that splits the vote. שמואל Shmuel
says if you're given the agency, you can't pass it
on, מילי לא מימסרן, but אומר אמרו is okay. You can appoint
a שליח שלא בפניו. shaliach shelo befanav. Okay? So therefore, back to
שמואל's Shmuel question. Remember שמואל's Shmuel question? When you said to two
people, write a גט, do you mean write or sign? So if
you meant sign, yes? If you mean sign, then what you're saying
is, you know, you can sign whoever you want to do the
writing. And that's essentially אומר אמרו, because whoever you find, I'm okay
with that person. I'm appointing the person that you find to do
the writing. Okay? And that would actually be okay, and therefore, that's
what שמואל Shmuel wants to know. If I meant just sign it,
so they can't hand over the signing,
but they could find somebody to scribe it, because that's אומר אמרו,
and אומר אמרו is okay. All right? Everybody good? Yes? All right,
moving on. Jonathan, you seem a little, a little stuck.
I was just thinking the underpinnings of אומר אמרו seem to be
the fear of distorting the message.
No, that is not correct. I mean, it is true that the
גמרא came up with that because of the חתם סופר issue, but
that is I would say that's a secondary issue. The primary issue
is whether you can have שליחות שלא בפניו, shlichus shelo befanav, right,
to represent the person. Yeah, side bar. Yeah, so try to bracket
that side bar the חתם סופר. Okay, so now the גמרא says
like this: גופא, Gufa, let's go back to that statement. אמר שמואל
אמר רבי הלכה כרבי יוסי דאמר מילי לא מימסרן לשליח. Amar Shmuel
amar Rebbi halacha keRabbi Yossi d'amar meili lo mimsaran l'shaliach. We rule
like רבי יוסי. אמר ליה רבי שמעון ברבי. Amar lei Rabbi Shimon
b'Rebbi. So רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon the son of רבי said, who,
right, because now שמואל Shmuel is saying this in the name of
רבי. So רבי שמעון רבי's Rabbi Shimon Rebbi son said, I don't
get that you're reporting that my father פסק pasken like רבי יוסי.
By the way, right, if we assume that right the משנה, Mishna,
which was authored, right, edited by רבי, like it sounds like the
משנה, the weight of the משנה is that you know you can
pass it on, right? You can, you know, tell three people תנו
and they can pass it on. רבי יוסי sort of, you know,
you got רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir you got this report from רבי
עקיבא, right, from prison, so that's so it's not exactly clear which
way the משנה was coming out. So here's what רבי's son said.
אמר רבי שמעון ברבי מאחר שרבי מאיר וחנינא איש אונו חולקים על
רבי יוסי. Amar Rabbi Shimon b'Rebbi me'achar sheRabbi Meir veChanina Ish Ono
cholkim al Rabbi Yossi. Given that in this משנה we've learned that
both רבי מאיר and חנינא איש אונו reporting from רבי עקיבא from
prison, who disagree with רבי יוסי and say that if you say
to a בית דין תנו that they can then that they can
delegate that, because you've basically given them the authority to delegate. So
מה ראה רבי לומר הלכה כרבי יוסי? mah ra'ah Rebbi lomar halacha
keRabbi Yossi? Why did, why are you saying that my father, you
know, what motivated my father to פסק pasken like רבי יוסי? So
אמר ליה, amar lei, so he said to him: שתוק בני שתוק,
shtok beni shtok, silence, my son, silence. ואי איתא את אילו לא
חזיתיה לרבי יוסי. ve'ita at ilu lo chaziseiah l'Rabbi Yossi. You've never
see you never saw רבי יוסי. You weren't זוכה zoiche to have
seen רבי יוסי. Apparently he had already passed on. אילו חזיתיה. ilulei
chaziseiah. Had you ever seen him, you would have realized that נימוקו
עמו. nimuko imo. That his reasoning is with him. So meaning, and
this is a famous phrase, רבי יוסי נימוקו עמו, Rabbi Yossi nimuko
imo, which means that anything רבי יוסי said was backed by like
very strong, thought out reason, and there's a presumption that we פסק
psak, like רבי יוסי. Okay? In the general הלכה כרבי יוסי שנימוקו
עמו. halacha keRabbi Yossi shenimuko imo. דתניא, Detanya, we learn
in a ברייתא, braisa, and this is from אבות דרבי נתן. Avos
D'Rabbi Natan. איסי בן יהודה היה מונה שבחן של חכמים. Isi ben
Yehudah hayah moneh shvachan shel chachamim. So here's a nice change of
tone or space. איסי בן יהודה Isi ben Yehudah would list the
praise of the sages in just interesting little like descriptors of the
sages. רבי מאיר חכם וסופר. Rabbi Meir chacham vesofeir. רבי מאיר was
a sage, was wise, and he actually happened to be a scribe.
Interesting because we're talking about scribes. יהודה, Yehudah, רבי יהודה חכם לכשירצה.
Rabbi Yehudah chacham l'cheshiyirtzeh. Look at
this wonderful compliment: he was very wise when he wanted to be.
Okay? As רש"י Rashi says, when he took the time to think
things through, whatever, he'd be very wise. Maybe he didn't always do
it. In the side it quotes from the ערוך Arukh that
says כשמפתח שפתיו הוא ראש המדברים. kshe-mefat-teach sfatav hu rosh ha-medabrim. So
I'm wondering if he's reading ירצה. yirtzeh. I don't know how I,
I don't know the grammar, but we have that in modern Hebrew,
right? להרצות lehartzoat means to give a lecture, right? Yes, everyone knows
that? No? להרצות, lehartzoat, anybody know modern Hebrew? I'm pretty sure it
means to give a lecture, right? So I'm wondering if the ערוך
Arukh is reading that, that he was a חכם chakham when it
came to opening up the discourse. But anyway, רש"י Rashi, says it
means when he would stop to think things through, he could be
very wise. ר' טרפון Rabbi Tarfon גבש של אגוזים. gash shel egozim.
ר' טרפון Rabbi Tarfon was a pile of nuts, which means what?
Which means like, like of walnuts or something. It means imagine you've
got this big pile of nuts and you take one, what happens?
They all collapse, fall down. So ר' טרפון, Rabbi Tarfon, you start
asking him something and then he says, and then this, and then
this, and then this, and then this, and like it all comes
pouring out when you, you know, whatever you ask him about.
No, it's a compliment, but it's just, it sort of means like,
you know, yeah, I know it sounds a little funny, but it
means like, you just get him started and like everything comes flooding
out.
Okay, שבחן של חכמים. shvachan shel chakhamim. ר' ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael חנות
מיוזנת. chanut meyuzenet. ר' ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael was a, was a stocked
store. Okay, anything you want, he, he can, you know, he has
all the information to give you, you know, and apparently he knows
where everything is located. Okay, ר' עקיבא Rabbi Akiva אוצר בלום. otzar
balum. ר' עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is a warehouse that is בלום. balum.
Now, רש"י, Rashi תוספות Tosafot debate exactly what the word means, but
essentially it means divided into compartments. And in אבות דרבי נתן Avot
d'Rabbi Natan it explains what this means as interest in terms of
ר' עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, because normally if you would ask me, right,
to say that you're a warehouse basically just means that you have
lots of knowledge, whereas by ר' עקיבא Rabbi Akiva we normally associate
him with his creativity. Right, I would have sort of said like,
you know, there's another משנה in פרקי אבות, Pirkei Avot, I forget
what that other משנה says about ר' עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, but like
the obvious, the obvious
sort of image that I would naturally associate with ר' עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva is the מעין המתגבר ma'ayan hamitgaber image, you know, this all
this tremendous creativity. So what is it said that he's a storehouse?
So the remainder of אבות דרבי נתן Avot d'Rabbi Natan there clarifies
it means that when he would learn from his רביים, rabbeim, right,
they would teach him like when you learn גמרא, like it would
all be mixed up, מדרש, Midrash, הלכה, analysis, משנה, it would all
be like, he'd learn it all together. And then he would come
home and he'd like sort it all out into the right compartment.
Because by the way, you know, the מדרשי הלכה, Midrashei Halakha, the
ספרי, Sifrei, the ספרא, Sifra, the whatever, were edited by the students
of ר' עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. Right, and you know, ר' ישמעאל Rabbi
Ishmael has parallel ones. So basically he took in all this information
and he systematized it. It's sort of like the רמב"ם, Rambam, right?
To think, I mean, I'm serious, like you think about the prodigious
feat that is, you take a look at this entire corpus and
you reorganize and systematize it. So that's what ר' עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
did.
ר' יוחנן בן נורי Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri קופת הרוכלים. kupat harochlim.
ר' יוחנן בן נורי Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri was like the, was
like the basket of the, you know, of the merchants that they,
who go from town to town and they'd have all these different
wares to sell. Not exactly sure how that's different from the חנות,
chanut, from the packed store. I guess, I guess it's smaller.
Oh, that's interesting. Yeah, not just your standard... Oh, that's a nice
idea. Okay, so it had the more unusual items. I like that.
Okay, ר' אלעזר בן עזריה Rabbi Eleazar ben Azariah קופת של בשמים.
kupat shel besamim. He was like the spice merchant. So רש"י Rashi
says that basically just the same idea except it's a little bit
smaller is what רש"י said. Okay.
משנת ר' אליעזר בן יעקב Mishnat Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov קב ונקי.
kav venaki. The teaching of ר' אליעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Eliezer ben
Yaakov is only a קב, kav, is a small measure, but it's
a very clean measure. Okay, so he doesn't say a lot, he
doesn't have a lot of things that he teaches, but what he
teaches is very well sort of like, you know, sifted and very
clean and very, you know,
very pure. So
presumably the presumption might be therefore that the few things he does
say, we would go like them. And ר' יוסי Rabbi Yosi נימוקו
עמו. nimuko imo. ר' יוסי, Rabbi Yosi, his reason is with him.
Which, it's funny, because you don't have the reason in the משנה.
And if anything you ask me, right, the more logical reason is
with
ר' מאיר Rabbi Meir and you know, and ר' חנינה Rabbi Chanina
here who have reported it from ר' עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, יתעלו בית
דין בירושלים תנו גט לאשתי, yit'elu beit din bi-Yerushalayim tenu get le-ishti,
the logic I would say would be that they can, that they
can appoint someone. But anyway, נימוקו עמו. nimuko imo.
Yes, is it possible נימוקו nimuko comes from עמוק, amok, for the
depth of the explanation, or נימוס, nimus, like law?
Oh,
so the law is with him. That's a nice explanation. So it's
just a way of saying we פוסקין pasken like ר' יוסי. Rabbi
Yosi. We don't know why, but we פוסקין pasken like ר' יוסי.
Rabbi Yosi. Yeah.
Right, he's authoritative.
He actually said in the משנה that he had a different tradition.
Okay, נימוקו עמו. nimuko imo. ר' שמעון Rabbi Shimon טוחן הרבה ומוציא
קימעא. tochein harbeh umotzi kima. ר' שמעון Rabbi Shimon grinds a lot
and and only comes out with a little. Now, that sounds like
an insult. Okay, but the גמרא is going to say what it
means. We're going to explain that.
תנא Tana משכח קימעא meshakheach kima ומה שמוציא... uma shemotzi... משכח קימעא,
meshakheach kima, he only forgets a little bit of his learning. So
מוציא motzi doesn't mean he produces a little, it means he he
expels a little, he gets rid of a little. Okay, he only
forgets a little bit. ומה שמוציא אינו מוציא אלא סובין. uma shemotzi
eino motzi ela subin. And the stuff that he forgets is only...
anyway is the bran, is the stuff he should have forgotten. Okay,
so, alright, וכן אמר רבי שמעון לתלמידיו *v'chen omar Rabbi Shimon l'talmidav*
בני *banai* and רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* says to his students, my
my children, שנו מדותי *shinu midotai* learn my, you know, my attributes
or as רש״י *Rashi* says it means, you might, that might mean
like learn how my my method, my methodology. רש״י *Rashi* also says
it means like just learn my teachings, like learn what I've taught
you, שמדותי תרומות מתרומות מדותיו של רבי עקיבא *shemidotai trumot mitrumot midotav
shel Rabbi Akiva* because they are the like, you know, the the
best of the best of the of the of the teachings or
of the methods of רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva*. Okay, so that was
a nice little break. Anyway, we פסקן pasken *paskin* like רבי יוסי
*Rabbi Yosi*. Now do we פסקן pasken *paskin* like רבי יוסי *Rabbi
Yosi* in both aspects, right? That מילי לא מימסרן *mili lo mimsaran*
and אומר אמרו *omer imru* is no good? It sounds like it,
because if אומר אמרו *omer imru* was good, then the בית דין
*Beit Din* בירושלים *bi'Yerushalayim* should be able to appoint someone else. Okay,
so that becomes a very restrictive ruling, at least by a גט
*get*, right? That everything has to be heard directly from the husband,
if we פסקן pasken *paskin* like רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yosi*. So now
the גמרא *Gemara* continues. גופא *Gufa*, אמר לשנים *omar l'shnayim*, now we're
going to get to see about this לא תעשה זאת בישראל *lo
ta'aseh zot b'Yisrael* and what that was about. אמר לשנים אמרו לסופר
ויכתוב ולפלוני ופלוני ויחתמו *omar l'shnayim imru l'sofer v'yichtov v'liploni u'ploni v'yachtomu*,
אמר רב הונא Rav Huna אמר רב *omar Rav Huna omar Rav*,
כשרה ולא תעשה זאת בישראל *keshera v'lo ta'aseh zot b'Yisrael*. So to
appoint someone to, now this is very strange, because to say כשרה
*keshera* would now sound like אומר אמרו *omer imru* is okay. So
maybe we're only פסקן pasken *paskin* like רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yosi* that
מילי *mili* is no good. Alright, so very strange here. Alright, so
you tell to two people to tell the סופר *sofer* and to
so-and-so to write, so everything you assign not in people's presence, אמר
רב *omar Rav* says that's good, ולא תעשה זאת בישראל *v'lo ta'aseh
zot b'Yisrael*. So why not? אמרו ליה לרב נחמן ואמרי ליה רב
נחמן Rav Nachman לעולא *amru lei l'Rav Nachman v'omri lei Rav Nachman
l'Ulla*, מאחר דכשרה *mei'achar d'keshera*, if it's כשרה *keshera*, אמאי לא תעשה
זאת בישראל *amai lo ta'aseh zot b'Yisrael*, why should you not do
this? So אמר ליה *omar lei*, חיישינן שמא תשכור עדים *chaishinan shema
tiskor edim*, ah, here's the reason. Nothing to do with any of
those issues we raised before about perverting the message. The concern
is if you have two עדים *edim* coming and saying the husband
told us that you should write a גט *get* and you should
sign the גט *get* for the wife, so maybe maybe they're lying,
right? Maybe the woman hired these witnesses to get to do this.
Now that by the way explains why you have to tell two
people. Why don't you just tell one person? Tell the סופר *sofer*,
tell the עדים *edim* and so on. Because that and certainly we'd
be afraid, how could the witnesses trust that this is what the
husband actually said? But even if it's two witnesses reporting it, we're
afraid the סופר *sofer* should, meaning, so we're not saying the husband
shouldn't say this, לא תעשה זאת בישראל *lo ta'aseh zot b'Yisrael* means
the סופר *sofer* and the עדים *edim* shouldn't accept the agency. I
am not going to trust, essentially it's a type of an אומר
אמרו *omer imru* problem, going back to you Jonathan, not on a
principle, not on like an עיקר הדין *ikar hadin* that it's not
valid, but on a concern about whether I'm really getting the real
information. On principle you should not listen to this person who's appointing
you because maybe they're really not representing the husband. Okay, that's why
לא תעשה זאת בישראל *lo ta'aseh zot b'Yisrael*. Because we're afraid that
she's hired witnesses. So the גמרא *Gemara* says, ומי חיישינן *umi chaishinan*,
are we really afraid of this? והתניא *v'hatanya*, עדים החתומים על שדה
מקח ועל גט אשה *edim hachtumim al sadeh mikach v'al get isha*,
לא חשו חכמים לדבר זה *lo chashu chachamim l'davar zeh*. They were
not, there's no concern. I mean what, we're going to be concerned
about every גט *get*, maybe it was forged? So the גמרא *Gemara*
says no. מעשה לא עבדי *ma'aseh lo avdi*. No, no. People won't
sign a document, they won't forge a document and sign it. That
they're not going to do. We're not afraid that the woman will
hire witnesses or that the witnesses will go along and agree to
actually forge a גט *get*. That they won't do. But דיבורא קאמרי
*dibura ka'amri*, that they themselves should not be personally implicated, they just
pass on the message, right? And then they're not directly involved in
the writing and the giving of the גט *get*, that you might
find two people that are willing to get be bribed and are
willing to do this. Okay, so that's a reasonable concern that the
woman hired these people, because they're not implicating themselves by signing the
גט *get*, they're just telling somebody else to do it, so therefore
we shouldn't listen to them because maybe the husband did not really
tell them. So now the גמרא *Gemara* says.
We means the last two.
Right, the סופר *sofer* and the עדים *edim* should not, should not
accept an appointment that's not directly from the husband. It's an אומר
אמרו *omer imru* problem but not for the אומר אמרו *omer imru*
reasons. Not because it wouldn't be binding, but because it might not
be genuine. Okay. Responsibility of the last person. Exactly, exactly. Because if
the woman has hired these witnesses, then
that's going to be, that's going to be happening. Okay, so the
גמרא *Gemara* says like this. דיבורא קאמרי *dibura ka'amri*. אמר לשנים *omar
l'shnayim*, אמר לשנים אמרו לסופר ויכתוב ואתם חתומו *omar l'shnayim imru l'sofer
v'yichtov v'atem chatomu*.
How about if the witnesses say we're going to sign, but we're
just telling the סופר *sofer* to write it? So now you've just
told me that there's no concern that the woman hired these witnesses,
because they're saying we're told by the husband, we're prepared to put
our name to it, we're going to sign, we're only asking you
to be the one to write it. So רב חסדא *Rav Chisda*
אמר כשרה *omar keshera*, fine, that's okay, כשרה ולא תעשה *keshera v'lo
ta'aseh*. Even that you shouldn't do. And here the only reason... is,
you know, גזירה this will lead to that. There's no real reason
you shouldn't do this, but if you allow this, then we're going
to wind up allowing the other case. So it winds up being
that in practice, if you say כשר ולא תעשה kasher velo taaseh
by both of these, in practice we sort at least פסקן אומר
אמרו is no good for other reasons because you're not even it's
no good but you shouldn't follow אומר אמרו because you it might
not be it might lead to not getting the real message from
the husband. Okay, רבה בר בר חנה Rabba bar bar Chuna אמר
no, that is כשר ותעשה kasher vetaaseh as long as the witnesses
are signing themselves, the סופר can go along and write it. רב
נחמן אמר כשר ולא תעשה, kasher velo taaseh, רב ששת Rav Sheshet
אמר כשר ותעשה, kasher vetaaseh, רבא Rava אמר כשר ולא תעשה, kasher
velo taaseh, רב יוסף Rav Yosef אמר כשר ותעשה, kasher vetaaseh, so
everybody has a different vote on this, okay, ואיכא דאפכי להו ve'ika
de'afchi lehu and some reversed what רבא Rava and רב יוסף Rav
Yosef said. Okay, of those do you even remember what רבא Rava
and רב יוסף Rav Yosef said, I read it so quickly? Okay
anyway, so it's really fascinating we פסקן like רב יוסף, Rav Yosef,
but it sounds like we don't fully פסקן like רב יוסף. Rav
Yosef. It sounds like we only פסקן מילי לא מימסרן לשליח, that
we don't because remember by the way, anyway, it sounds like when
שמואל Shmuel said הלכה כרבי יוסי halacha keRabbi Yossi דמילי לא מימסרן
לשליח, de'mili lo mimsran leshalich, like שמואל Shmuel himself really split the
פסק, he did not go רבי יוסי fully. שמואל Shmuel said אומר
אמרו is okay. And that's the end of the גמרא as well.
אומר אמרו is okay, you can appoint a שליח שלא בפניו shelo
befanav and have somebody report to that person. However, לא תעשה כן,
that you shouldn't be doing that because we're afraid that they might
not really be hearing it from the husband. Okay, so that's but
technically that is okay.
Yeah, I think this is just the last one that's stated?
No, not necessarily, especially when it comes down in pairs like this.
Yes. Okay. אמר לעשרה כתבו גט, amar le'asara kitvu get, now the
last part of the משנה, you tell ten people write it. So
if you didn't say כולכם, kulcham. it means, it means from among
you, some of you need to write it and give it. If
you said כולכם, kulcham. it means you all have to be involved.
תנו רבנן, tanu rabbanan, אמר לעשרה כתבו גט ותנו לאשתי, amar le'asara
kitvu get utnu le'ishti, אחד כותב על ידי כולם, echad kotev al
yedei kulam, one person just writes on behalf of them, which basically
means just one person has to write, they don't all have to
write. כולכם כתובו, kulchem ktovu, all of you write it, אחד כותב
במעמד כולם, echad kotev bemaamad kulam, so how are you going to
get everybody to write it? So it means everybody is present and
one person it's sort of like a שליח ציבור, shaliach tzibur, you
know, you know, where he's like the whole ציבור tzibur is praying,
that's the way רב סולובייצ'יק Rav Soloveitchik explained, such a beautiful explanation.
He said the difference between תפילת לחש tefillat lachash במניין beminyan and
חזרת הש"ץ chazarat hashatz is that תפילת לחש tefillat lachash is תפילה
בציבור, tefillah betzibur, everybody's דאבנינג davening as individuals in the presence of
a ציבור, tzibur, and the repetition of the שמונה עשרה shmoneh esrei
is תפילת הציבור. tefillat hatzibur. The whole community is דאבנינג davening as
one unit through the through the mouthpiece of the שליח ציבור. shaliach
tzibur. He's representing the entire unit of the congregation. So that's why
if you have everybody standing there and one person is writing it,
that's like we're all writing it. Okay, so that satisfies all writing
it. אחד כותב במעמד כולם. echad kotev bemaamad kulam. הוליכו גט לאשתי,
holichu get le'ishti, bring a גט to my wife, אחד
מוליך על ידי כולם, echad molich al yedei kulam, one brings it
for all of them meaning it's meaning one of you guys bring
it. כולכם הוליכו, kulchem holichu, all of you bring the גט, אחד
מוליך במעמד כולם, echad molich bemaamad kulam, they all have to get
on the plane together, they all have to right one brings it
in everybody now I don't know what that means, every step of
the way they all have to be there? Can a guy take
a little bit of a break and do some sightseeing and catch
up with the group a little later on? I mean I'm serious.
Like what at what stage, you know, does every step have to
be it's another question by the way that's really the ראשונים rishonim
ask, which is can you send a גט in the mail? When
you make a שליח להולכה, shaliach leholacha, is it really the conveying
of the גט that's the שליחות shlichus, or really it's the end
stage, it's just the giving of the גט that's the שליחות, so
it doesn't matter how it's physically gets to the right place, right?
So anyway, so presumably that more means one gives it in everybody's
presence. Okay,
כולם ואחד מוליך במעמד כולם. kulam ve'echad molich bemaamad kulam. איבעיא להו,
iba'ya lehu, now they raise a question. מנה אותן מהו, mana otan
mahu, if he says one, two, three, four, five, six, seven, eight,
nine, ten, give a גט to my wife. So what do we
say the counting means? Does it mean all of you, or does
it mean from among you? Okay, now here you see by the
way according to the גמרא it's not אסור assur to count people.
Okay, maybe it means you did הושיעה את עמך. hoshia et amecha.
I don't know מהו. mahu. רב הונא אמר מנה אינו ככולכם, mana
eino kechulchem, that does not count like you said all of you,
it means any of you.
רב
יוחנן משום רבי אלעזר דמין רומי Rav Yochanan mishum Rabbi Eliezer demin
Romi אמר says מנה הרי הוא ככולכם, mana harei hu kechulchem, no
when you count them it's like you mean everybody I counted has
to do it. אמר רב פפא amar Rav Papa ולא פליגי, velo
pligi, they don't debate, הא דמנה כולהו הא דמנה מקצתייהו. ha demana
kulhu ha demana miktzatyu. The difference is did you count everybody in
the room or did you only count some people in the room?
אמרי להאי גיסא ואמרי להאי גיסא, amri lehai gisa ve'amri lehai gisa,
now which way does it go? So there's a debate. Some say
if you count everybody, that more means everyone do it, whereas if
you counted some it just means, yeah, some of you do it,
whatever. And some say the reverse. If you counted some, then you're
then you're focusing on a subgroup. So if you only counted half
the people in the room, it means you that I've counted I
want all of you to do it. Whereas if I count all
of them, I just somehow mean from among you do it. It's
hard to exactly understand the argument either way. But anyway, okay, so
whether counting means everyone or from among you could make a difference
if you counted everyone or counted some, but you could argue that
either way.
Now If you're singling them out, you're doing it intentionally. But do
you mean from among the five I've counted, from you five, see
that again is given to my wife, or do I mean all
of you five? Right? So that's the question. And which one more
would indicate I mean everybody? All right, so now the גמרא
ends, אתקין רב יהודה בגיטא דכולכם, atkin Rav Yehuda be-Gitta de-kulcham, that
רב יהודה Rav Yehuda made a תקנה takkana that when a husband
wants to say כולכם, kulcham, that they should know that there's a
particular נוסח, nusach, and he wanted to make the נוסח nusach a
way in which it would not lead to the problems, basically to
make it not mean כולכם. kulcham. So here's the נוסח nusach you
should say when you're doing a
כולכם. kulcham כתבו או כולכם או כולכם או כל חד מנכון. Ktovu
o kulcham o kulcham o kol chad minichon. You guys write the
גט, I don't care if it's everyone or if it's any one
of you.
חתמו שניים או כולכם או כל תרי מנכון Chasomu shenayim o kulcham
o kol traie minichon or any two of you. והובילו Ovilu bring
it, או כולכם או כל חד מנכון. o kulcham o kol chad
minichon. So have the husband explicitly say either all or everyone, so
we don't have to worry that everyone wasn't there. Because obviously if
you say כולכם, kulcham it's making it much harder to do. אמר
רבא, Amar Rava, no, זימנין דגזליה לדיבוריה, zimnin de-gazleh le-diburay, ואמר כולכם
ולא אמר כל חד מנכון. ve-amar kulcham ve-lo amar kol chad minichon.
That's not a good way to say it. Don't say write a
גט all of you or any one of you. Why start with
the all of you? The all of you is the problem. He'll
just say all of you and he won't finish the end of
the sentence. ואתי ליפסולי ve-ati le-ipsooleh and it'll become פסול. posul. אלא
אמר רבא, Ella amar Rava, here's what you say: כתבו כל חד
מנכון, Ktovu kol chad minichon, basically just establish a text that doesn't
even acknowledge the idea of כולכם. Write it, any one of you.
חתמו כל תרי מנכון, Chasomu kol traie minichon, any two of you.
והובילו כל חד מנכון. Ovilu kol chad minichon. So basically teach people
a text that doesn't lead to saying כולכם because כולכם is just
asking for trouble. Okay, הדרן עלך האומר. Hadran alach ha-omer. All right.